<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A magazine of scandall. Or, a heape of wickednesse of two infamous ministers, consorts, one named Thomas Fowkes of Earle Soham in Suffolk, convicted by law for killing a man, and the other named Iohn Lowes of Brandeston, who hath beene arraigned for witchcraft, and convicted by law for a common barrettor. Together with the manner how my Lord of Canterbury would put and keep them in the ministery, notwithstanding the many petitions and certificates from their parishioners, and others, presented to him, they being the head and most notorious of the scandalous ministers within the county of Suffolke, and well may be said of all England. And against whom as chiefe of the scandalous ministers the county of Suffolke have petitioned to the Parliament: and desired to bee seene by Parliament, because herein is something mentioned, which is conceived, that one of these scandalous ministers have abused the authority of the Lords in Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E137_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9987</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873642</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873642</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 24:E137[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A magazine of scandall. Or, a heape of wickednesse of two infamous ministers, consorts, one named Thomas Fowkes of Earle Soham in Suffolk, convicted by law for killing a man, and the other named Iohn Lowes of Brandeston, who hath beene arraigned for witchcraft, and convicted by law for a common barrettor. Together with the manner how my Lord of Canterbury would put and keep them in the ministery, notwithstanding the many petitions and certificates from their parishioners, and others, presented to him, they being the head and most notorious of the scandalous ministers within the county of Suffolke, and well may be said of all England. And against whom as chiefe of the scandalous ministers the county of Suffolke have petitioned to the Parliament: and desired to bee seene by Parliament, because herein is something mentioned, which is conceived, that one of these scandalous ministers have abused the authority of the Lords in Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for R. H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the right reverend father in God, William Archbishop of Canterbury, the humble petition and information of some of the inhabitants of Earle Soham in Suffolke.." p. 12-13.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fowkes, Thomas.</term>
               <term>Laud, William, 1573-1645.</term>
               <term>Lowes, John, --  of Brandeston.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Suffolk (England) --  History --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MAGAZINE OF SCANDALL.</p>
            <p>OR, A heape of wickedneſſe of two infamous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, conſorts, one named <hi>Thomas Fowkes</hi> of Earle Soham in Suffolk, convicted by Law for killing a man, and the other named <hi>Iohn Lowes</hi> of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſton, who hath beene arraigned for witchcraft, and convicted by law for a common Barrettor.</p>
            <p>Together with the manner how my Lord of Canterbury would put and keep them in the Miniſtery, notwithſtanding the many Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions and Certificates from their Pariſhioners, and others, preſented to him, they being the head and moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious of the ſcandalous Miniſters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the County of Suffolke, and well may be ſaid of all England.</p>
            <p>And againſt whom as chiefe of the ſcandalous Miniſters the County of Suffolke have petitioned to the Parliament: And deſired to bee ſeene by the Parliament, becauſe herein is ſomething men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, which is conceived, that one of theſe ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Miniſters have abuſed the authority of the Lords in Parliament.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And he that killeth any man ſhall ſurely be put to death:</p>
               <bibl>Levit. 24.17.21. Num. 35.18. &amp;c.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Non ſolum lutum verum &amp; ne tange venenum.</q>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>R. H.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156500:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156500:2"/>
            <head>A Magazine of Scandall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I ſhould goe about to declare all the devices and evill practices that could be ſaid concerning theſe two, namely, this common Barretor, and this man-killer, it were an endleſſe peece of worke, and labour without end; but having an intent to ſhoot at ſome few, which the leaſt of them are too notorious and too intolerable to be ſuffered in the Church of Chriſt. I will avoid prolixity, and therefore omit in particular the many vexatious troubles and ſuits that theſe two have troubled their pariſhioners and Neighbours in the townes about them, how many they have undone and beggered to the terror of many others: I will forbeare to tell you how many were every Court day toſſed and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the Commiſſaries Court, ſo as the common proverbe was, that they had made a more beaten roade and footpath to the Commiſſaries Court, then any market path in all the County; I will not tell how many deſperat deboiſt baſe and vild perſons, and ſome that have been three or foure times arraigned for felony were their dependants, and went with them from Court to Court, from Aſſizes to Aſſizes, and from Seſſions to Seſſions, to act, accompliſh, and performe any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and deſperat deviſes, either by their falſe oathes or deſperat forces and violences, and many times ſome of them by pretence of being Bailiffs to arreſt men, have entred into mens houſes, and taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their goods, nothing eſcaped if it were not too hot or too heavy; I will not publiſh in what deſperat manner theſe two have joyned with theſe deboiſt Bailiffes <hi>Conjunctim &amp; diviſim</hi> iojntly and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in their deſperat oathes to accompliſh their evill ends, and how they have ſhared in their booties which theſe their dependants have ſo unlawfully purloined<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I will not expreſſe the many wrongs, ſuits and controverſies, they labour and ſeeke after to oppreſſe others and worke thereby their owne profit and advantage, as namely in inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:156500:3"/>after broken titles and buying of them but never pay for them, in hiring and entring upon any lands where there is any controverſie, and ſo to occupy the ſame for a very ſmall matter, or for nothing at all, which is unlawfull in a Miniſter to occupy any temporall lands at all, and if neighbors pariſhioners be at any controverſie with his Miniſter for his tithes, then one or both of theſe are the Antagoniſts and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions to buy theſe tithes, and will be ſure to terrifie the poore pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner that he muſt <hi>fas</hi> or <hi>nefas,</hi> due or not due pay what is demanded. To ſpeake how theſe bend their ſhoulders to uphold one another in their practices, and concurre and hang together, it were too tedious: And ſeverally how they uſe their ſeverall poſtures and qualities apart, the firſt, I meane the Mankiller ſetting all thought of his function aſide as no part of his calling, doth in as ample husbandlike manner as any husbandman whatſoever go to his labour (when other practices faile) as to ditch, plowe, threſh, carry muck, dreſſe his horſes, and eſpecially on Sunday mornings, and comes to Church with his coat full of horſe haires, for he keepes a teame of horſes, and goes by the rode to carry timber to Woodbridge and Ipſwich, or any other carriage as duely as any carter by the Rode whatſoever, being one indeed cut out for ſuch a purpoſe rather then for the place he hath beene ſuffered to hold, being likewiſe of a deſperate condition, his hands having been in blood, have threatned divers of his adverſaries to hurt or wound them, and to that end hath carried about him a moſt dangerous ſharpe weapon comprehended cloſly in a ſtaffe, divers others he hath with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence beaten and wounded, yea rather then he would be out of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he will beat his owne wife who hath had a feeling in this cauſe, he hath ſo feared divers of his pariſh &amp; others with ſuits for no cauſe, moſt certain it is that he hath extracted and drawn divers ſeveral great ſums of money both from the able and unable, rather then they would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his vexations, and upon every occaſion threatens my Lord of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury his warrant and great punniſhments from my Lord of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, and who but my Lord of Canterbury, upon whoſe preſumption he was ſo audacious that he durſt doe any thing, yea in the very act of receiving the Communion, in the preſence of neere a hundred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, moſt of them kneeling at the Railes, in the Chancell, where he forced them to come, ſome of them having received the Sacrament and others ready to receive it, in a moſt ſcandalous and irreligious manner railed and uſed moſt menacing ſpeeches, threatning my Lord of Canterburies warrant, and therewith would fetch them up, uſing foule tearmes, and would not adminiſter the Sacrament to the reſt that ſat there kneeling and ready to receive it as aforeſaid, but in reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:156500:3"/>tearmes turned them away: And further his impudence is ſo great, that during the time of this preſent Parliament in Michaelmas tearme laſt, and divers times ſince he hath confronted the authority of the Lords houſe of Parliament, as upon the declaration the honourable houſe will judge one <hi>Margaret Borret</hi> widdow, having gotten an order by petition from the Committee for Petitions from that honorable horſe, which did reflect upon this <hi>Thomas Fowkes,</hi> this <hi>Fowkes</hi> to croſſe that order made a moſt ſtrong affidavit, of which hee will never be wanting if need require, and therby got an order in ſome ſort oppoſing the former order, but with this he muſt have his order (as he ſaid) under the authority as well of the Lords ſpirituall as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, or elſe is was nothing worth, and ſo had and hath often boaſted that this order from the Committee was nothing worth, becauſe it wanted the authority of the Lords ſpirituall, and that his order had the Lords ſpirituall mentioned therein, and the order from the Committee had not, as by the ſeverall orders now remaining in the ſaid Lords houſe appear, and ſo maks by his ſpeeches and reports the ſaid order of the Committee to be of no validity, becauſe it wants the authority of the Lords ſpirituall as his hath, and in theſe and many the like, I might go on and have no roome left for an end. I will alſo give you a taſt of the other, I meane the common Barrettor; this title ſhewes him of a pragmatick diſpoſition, he is nimble as a dancer, he will trip it from market to market, yea to London (being a great Solicitor both at common law and ſpirituall) and enters into every mans buſineſſe that will have him or imploy him, and takes upon him to adviſe more then all the Counſell in thoſe parts, and declares himſelfe to have more knowledge in the lawes of the Kingdome then the beſt Lawyer of them all, and indeed it hath proved ſomething to that purpoſe, for he hath adviſed many to their undoing: I will tell you of one excellent point of learning he practiſed, that is, he would preſſe to be an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trator for men in many cauſes, perſwading both parties thereunto, promiſing either party to doe what ſhould be required, but to be ſure he ſerved his owne turne, and takes mony of both parties, but he that gave leaſt was ſure to be ſoundly cruſhed if not undone, <hi>probatumeſt.</hi> A pretty conceit he had to bring a poore taylor within compaſſe of the law, to whom he ought a ſpleene, whoſe honeſt condition was not ſutable to his, being a man of ſuch ſobriety and conſtancy that this pragmatick Barretor could not in the ſpace of two years find occaſion to vex him, at laſt making himſelfe familiar and loving to the taylor, ſent for him upon a Sunday morning to come unto him, and being in his bed deſired the taylor to mend his briches preſently, for he was to
<pb facs="tcp:156500:4"/>put them on, which the taylor very ſimply did, but before the that day after which was the next Court day, this Barrettor cited him to the Court, and made the poore taylor know it was not lawfull to mend britches on the Sabbath day. I can tell you this Barrettor or prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke is alſo a brave Phyſitian and Chirurgian, and can doe more hurt in one houre then the beſt Phyſitian can doe good in a yeare, he hath much practiſed this art; And for a ſouldier he could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered more by his art and military skill, then ever Generall <hi>Leſly</hi> or <hi>Spinola,</hi> or any other great Commander in the world, for he can build caſtlos in the aire, and he much wondred (as he ſaid) why the King did not ſend for him when the Iſle of Rees vioage was, who could have preſcribed a way to have ſaved the lives of all the Commanders, and wonne all the Country; what ſhould I ſay of theſe two that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be in the place of paſtors and teachers of the people but as, <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cateline, nullum ſcelus niſi per te, nullum facinus niſi per te, nullum flagitium ſine te,</hi> for there is ſcarce an evell project thereabouts but is hammered upon their Anvile. Their Religion is either none, or elſe as the wind blows: If the ceremonies be tending to Popery, none ſo forward as they, and if there be orders cleane contrary they ſhal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed any Round-head in the Ile of great Brittain; they both daily have frequented the company of knowne popiſh Recuſants, entertained ſome of them, and lodged them, nay which is more, they have had the helpe, adviſe, and aſſiſtance of popiſh Recuſants in many their vild and abhominable actions, and have had them for their greateſt and chiefeſt confederates, agents, and counſellors to procure themſelves the unjuſt getting and obteining of mony, goods, and other advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. This Barretor (to make ſhort): hath beene ſo vehemently ſuſpected of witchcraft, that he hath beene twice indicted, and once arraigned for witchcraft.</p>
            <p>Whether it be ſo or not, it is moſt certaine that many have ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him upon their deaths, and it is moſt certaine that he hath uſed the ſociety and helpe of thoſe that have beene convicted and executed for witchcraft; for whom he proteſted he would pawne his ſoule for theirs, and his body for their bodies, and hath had the ſociety and daily frequentation of divers others that are vehemently ſuſpected for witches, and without doubt hath had the helpe of ſuch to worke his intended purpoſes, and to further his deare brother in iniquity the man killer, as brethren which comply together to deſtroy all their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers. And hath declared that if he were proſecuted by his Pariſhioners, and that they obtained their wills againſt him in putting him out of his Benefice, then quoth he, there are ſome of their houſes on fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="tcp:156500:4"/>their eares, two hundred miles hence is as good for me as here. <hi>Quis audivit talia horribilia?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One having loſt certaine ſilver ſpoones, the Barrettor ſent poſt horſe and man to one <hi>Woolward</hi> a notorious reputed Conjurer, to helpe him to the ſaid plate, repoſing (as it ſeemes) truſt in the devill to help him to what he deſires. Now theſe two brethren in iniquity dwell within a mile or little more one of another, and are concomitants, fellow Coach-horſes, and draw juſt together. Theſe went to Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Fayre together, and bought much of the trinkets that have been reported there to have beene ſold; and I beleeve they payd well for them, for they have had ſpeciall Popiſh ware, and they have made as good uſe of their ware as any within the kingdome of England.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay? all this, <hi>&amp; mille talia,</hi> which might have beene declared, were but talke and bare accuſation, if proofes did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Therefore (in a word) I will tell you, the one is by law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed for killing a man, being a very ſome act, and ſo declared by Iudge <hi>Crooke,</hi> for he did beat out a mans braines: and the other hath beene arraigned for Witchcraft, and convicted by Law for a common Barrettor, both lately tried upon their ſeverall traverſes at Bury Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes in Suffolke; the common Barrettor before Mr. Iuſtice <hi>Barkeley,</hi> the man-killer before Mr. Iuſtice <hi>Crooke,</hi> as by the ſeverall Records appeare, and one of them for the common Barrettor exemplified, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which Records there is no averment or denyall. And theſe are the two for which the Petition of Suffolke againſt ſcandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters is chiefly and principally grounded. And thus I doubt not theſe things appearing to bee true, which are ready at all times to bee ſhewne, ſome remaining on Record, and all the reſt to be depoſed by many witneſſes, will give ſatisfaction of the truth herein.</p>
            <p>And now I come to ſhew you how my Lord of Canterbury would and did hold and ſupport theſe two precious ſervants of his ſcill in the Miniſtery.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:156500:5"/>
               <head>The manner how my Lord of Canterbury would keepe them in the Miniſtry notwithſtanding the many Petitions and Certificates from their neighbors and others preſented unto him, they being the head of the ſcandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, againſt whom the County of Suffolke have petitioned.</head>
               <p>AFter the former taſt given of the outward comportment of theſe two rare birds, I would that it might be a little underſtood of the inward matter they are indued withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I mean as touching their ability of learning and divinity, for I make accompt by the former diſcourſe that they cannot have much inward grace, for they never ſought for that at Lambeth faire, neither do I think that any was thereto be ſold, therefore I will apply my ſelfe to the other, I meane their learning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you may underſtand what good cauſe my Lord of Canterbury had ſo ſtrongly to keep them in the Miniſtry: it may be thought that it was their great learning; Indeed as for that, they had learning enough to preach againſt them that would not pay treble their tithes and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt ſuch as they bore malice, and that in many unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting termes out of points of learning or divinity, but I would know firſt whether they can read well or no, for I am ſure that neither of them can write true Engliſh, yet they endeavour to read their ſermons, which I would not condemne if they were penned conducing to the interpretation of the Scriptures, and not from any malicious ſpirit: Scholers they are I confeſſe, and had need to go to ſchoole ſtill, for one of them being demanded what <hi>Microcoſmus</hi> was, which by interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſignifieth a little world, anſwered that it was Latin for a miſt or fog; the demandant replyed againe it was true, for it was more then a miſt, for ſure he was in a great cloud of darkneſſe: and one of them at another time being demanded what <hi>Plerophoria</hi> ſignified, which ſignifies, fulneſſe of faith, he anſwered that he did not like that word, becauſe (as he thought) the Papiſts did attribute it to the names of pictures and reliques; and the demandant replied againe that hee thought he did not like that word indeed, and believed, that he would never be brought to like it, but <hi>quid moramur in iſtis?</hi> let us follow our
<pb facs="tcp:156500:5"/>text, and tell you how my Lord of Canterbury would not by no meanes be informed nor perſwaded to heare any thing againſt theſe two for divers of the neighbours having deſired their Solicitor to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent divers petitions and certificates to his Lordſhip againſt the ſaid <hi>Fowkes,</hi> and of his conviction for killing the man, and alſo to informe him of the ſaid <hi>Lowes,</hi> how he was convicted for a common Barretor, amongſt many other of the foule actions of them both: And it muſt be underſtood that this <hi>Fowkes</hi> was <hi>ipſo facto</hi> out of his function upon his conviction, untill the Lords great grace of Canterbury tooke great care to put in great good Miniſters, and ſo put him in againe, and gave him a diſpenſation; but before his diſpenſation, the ſaid Solicitor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented under the hands of his, the <hi>Fowkes,</hi> his neighbours and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, a Certificate of his ſcandalous life, and of his little deſert both in life and doctrine, which was at that time received by Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> his Secretary, and my Lords Grace took ſpeciall notice therof, and kept it, and ſtill hath it, which to any mans judgement had been enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Biſhop in the Chriſtian world not to have diſpenced with a man whoſe hands were in blood, and convicted for killing of a man, which had beene much if he had received a Certificate of the ſaid <hi>Fowkes</hi> honeſt life, and converſation; but howſoever there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing weighed well with my Lord or Maſter <hi>Dell,</hi> or both, to induce my Lord to give him a diſpenſation: But to the Miniſtry my Lord did reſtore him, by what Law or Canon none can warrant, for none whoſe hands have beene in blood ought there to remaine, which being heard and knowne, to the aſtoniſhment of many well governed and able Miniſters, as other laymen and religious people, conceived at firſt that my Lord of Canterbury was abuſed, preſuming hee would not have done it, and thereupon at the like requeſt of the pariſhioners and others, the ſaid Solicitor addreſſed himſelfe with new petitions from time to time, but now none would be accepted, read, or heard, many of which are ſtill to be ſeene: And the ſaid Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was changed, the Solicitor received nothing but rough ſpeeches, yea threats ſometimes, and told him we might have remedy in the high Commiſſion, and no anſwer could be had, but, goe to the high Commiſſion: And my Lord of Canterbury being once preſſed by the ſame Solicitor, ſaid, Away, would you have me undoe a man for an unlucky blow? whereas nothing was required but that he might be put <hi>ab officio,</hi> but not <hi>à beneficio,</hi> only ayming to have him ſuſpended from ſo holy a function, that with quiet minds his pariſhioners might come to Church to ſerve God without brawlings and railings on the Sabbath dayes, yea in the time of receiving the Communion, with
<pb facs="tcp:156500:6"/>which they were dayly vexed and troubled by him the ſaid <hi>Fowkes,</hi> but my Lord did excuſe the matter and alledged, that he had Certificate from divers of the Iudges, that his cauſe was to be pittied, and that he ſhould kill a man in kindneſſe, or ſomething to that effect as hee ſaid, which no man will ever believe that any Iudge will excuſe any man after a conviction by law; but it is moſt certaine that Maſter Iuſtice <hi>Crooke</hi> before whom he was tried, never would give the leaſt counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance either in word or writing to extenuate ſo foule a fact, and none elſe could (but before whom the triall was) declare how the caſe deſerved: And ſo after many repulſes, and rejections, the pariſhioners and others were forced <hi>(volens nolens)</hi> to ceaſe their juſt complaint, and ſo reſt untill it was conceived that my Lord of Canterbury might better conſider of his former paſſages, hoping he might be humbled by his reſtraint in the Tower, and to ſalve ſuch things as before hee had done; they were adviſed to repaire to him there, and at their ſaid requeſt the Solicitor did repaire to him in the Tower, who then ſeemed to incline and to give eare to their requeſt, and ſeemed as if hee would countermand his former diſpenſation, ſo as they could procure ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing under Iudge <hi>Crooke</hi> his hand of the true and juſt deſert of the fact, whereupon the ſaid Iudge being ſpoken withall to that purpoſe, anſwered, that what would my Lord of Canterbury have a better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction then a conviction by law, and if that were not ſufficient it muſt be queſtioned whether the ſaid <hi>Fowkes</hi> had a lawfull triall or not; whereupon a little before Michaelmas laſt, the ſaid Solicitor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine repaired to him in the Tower, and becauſe all matters of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection might be taken away? <hi>viz.</hi> the alledged certificate from the Iudges, and his pretence that he did nothing but upon good grounds, the ſaid Solicitor preſented him with this petition and information, with an affidavit annexed herein, after mentioned, and there withall ſhewed him the exemplification under ſeale of the Conviction of the ſaid <hi>Lowes</hi> of common Barrery, requiring him <hi>(ſede vacante)</hi> that he would not ſuffer ſuch in the Miniſtry, yet it ſeemes he could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with the waight that did hang ſo heavy on the other party, but raited a new excuſe, and anſwered the ſaid Solicitor, that by reaſon there was an act of Parliament that the high Commiſſion was taken away (which ſeemed to ſtick hard in his ſtomacke) the had no power to put out any out of the Miniſtry, were they never ſo bad, with other allegations; but the ſaid Solicitor anſwered, that hee hoped although that the high Commiſſion was taken away, yet as long as hee was Biſhop of Canterbury his power was not taken away to doe the Church right in ſuſpending ſcandalous Miniſters, or at leaſt to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb facs="tcp:156500:6"/>that his diſpenſation which was conceived not to be juſtly done, and likewiſe to put out a common Barrettor, ſo convicted by law, as by the Record which was then ſhewed unto him under ſeale did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, which was an evidence of it ſelfe without further proofe or witneſſes: but nothing would prevaile, neither could his Lordſhip give any reaſons to avoid this ſaid enſuing Petition or Information, which will more plainly ſet forth the ſubſtance of his wilfull perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in retayning ſuch wicked and prophane perſons in the Church, the tenour whereof followes, with an Affidavit annexed in theſe words, <hi>verbatim &amp; literatim,</hi> hee himſelfe receiving the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, with the Affidavit, under Maſter <hi>Page</hi> his hand, one of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Chancery, and doth keepe them untill this preſent. Divers other materiall matters depending upon this cauſe could be manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if they might be examined. But I hope this will ſuffiſe to expell theſe two ſcandalous conſorts, that infect both Church and Common wealth, and all ſuch that are of like condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:156500:7"/>
               <head>Here followeth the Petition and Information with the Affidavit, preſented <hi>verbatim</hi> to the Archbiſhop.</head>
               <div type="petition">
                  <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of Canterbury.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition and Information of ſome of the Inhabitants of Earle Soham in Suffolke, and divers other neighbours adjoyning.</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat whereas your Grace hath given diſpenſation to <hi>Thomas Fowkes</hi> of Earle Soham aforeſaid, Clerke, after he was convicted by Law for felony and man-ſlaughter, your Grace alledging you did it upon good ground, having a Certificate from Iudges and Iuſtices: We therefore, being adviſed by Councell, doe offer your Grace theſe reaſons to the contrary, to be no ground, nor ſafe for your Lordſhip.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, for that by lawfull tryall at an Aſſizes he ſtands convict of the fact, which is enough, if no more were ſaid.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, that no Certificate from either Iudge or Iuſtice ought to be by your Lordſhip admitted, whereby you ſhould doe any thing againſt any Iudgement or Confiction by Law.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That if it were allowable that any Certificate either from Lords or any great perſonages whatſoever, ſhould ſet a man right after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction by Law, no man would ever want a Certificate by one friends meanes or other, which would bee even the overthrow of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawes of the Kingdome, and they that allow ſo doe no leſſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fourthly, if the King himſelfe ſhould bee perſwaded, or rather
<pb facs="tcp:156500:7"/>ſeduced to cauſe your Lordſhip, or any other, bearing authority under him, to doe any thing againſt any Iudgement or Conviction of Law, it ſhould be your Lordſhips part and duty to perſwade the King to the contrary, and not to doe it, being the Law hath paſſed.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Fiftly, it doth not appeare to what end the Certificate from the Iudges and Iuſtices was obtained, for if it had beene to doe any thing againſt a conviction they would never have granted or done it, but it ſeemed the ſaid <hi>Fowkes</hi> made the beſt uſe of it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sixtly, Iudge <hi>Crooke</hi> hath beene ſpoke withall to certifie of the offence, whoſe anſwer was, If a conviction at law were not a Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate enough of the fact: Then it muſt be queſtioned whether the ſaid <hi>Fowkes</hi> had a lawfull triall or no.</p>
                  <p>It will be alledged againſt your Grace that you urged this cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your predeceſſor Archbiſhop <hi>Abbot,</hi> whoſe cauſe was far more to be tollerated then this.</p>
                  <p>It will be urged and proved what free acceſſe the ſaid <hi>Fowkes</hi> had to your Grace and to your Secretary, with divers conferences, and what rejections have been to your Petitioners and their Certificates and Petitions from time to time profered, but never accepted, and your Lordſhip being once preſt upon, your Lordſhip very angerly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that you would not undoe a man for an unlucky blow.</p>
                  <p>Neither was it or is it deſired to have him undone, but onely that he may be taken <hi>ab officio,</hi> but not <hi>à beneficio,</hi> having onely our ends to be quiet in the Church, having often threatned us with puniſhments your Lordſhip ſhould inflict, even in the time of receiving the Communion, and many other matters which by Certificate may appeare moſt irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, but never were admitted to be ſeene before the ſaid <hi>Fowkes</hi> made meanes to your Lordſhip. Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> gently did receive one Certificate, which ſtill he hath, but never after would ſuffer any to bee ſeene.</p>
                  <p>Pleaſe your Lordſhip to call to mind whom you have put out of the Miniſtry, and whom you keep in.</p>
                  <p>Pleaſe your Lordſhip to ſee the affidavit annexed.</p>
                  <p>Pleaſe your Lordſhip to ſee a Record exemplified under ſeale, that one <hi>Iohn Lowes</hi> of Brandeſton in Suffolke, Clerke, is convicted for a common Barrettor, and to doe with him <hi>(ſede vacante)</hi> according to Law, it is evidence of it ſelfe, and there is no averment againſt a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſo likewiſe in the former cauſe.</p>
                  <p>We deſire not to trouble your Lordſhip nor our ſelves no further, if it ſhall ſo pleaſe your Grace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="affidavit">
                  <pb facs="tcp:156500:8"/>
                  <head>Here followeth the Affidavit annexed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.S.</hi> of Woodbridge in the County of Suffolke Gent. maketh oath that he knowes and hath ſeene <hi>Iohn Lowes</hi> of Brandeſton in Suffolke, Clerke, twice indirected, and once arraigned for witchcraft, and knowes him to be convicted by law for a common Barettor upon a full triall at the Aſſiſes in Suffolke, as by record under ſeale appeares: he maketh oath alſo that <hi>Thomas Fowkes</hi> of Earle Soham in Suffolke, Clerke, is of a very ſcandalous life, and hath heard many of his neighbours and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers complaine of him, and have ſet their hands againſt him for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſcandalous matters concerning his life and converſation, and more eſpecially for railing and threatning often them with my Lord of Canterbury, even in the time of receiving the Communion upon Eaſter day, and another day: and moreover this deponent knowes that he hath been very converſant with Popiſh Recuſants, and knows and have beene the greateſt inſtruments for him to effect and bring to paſſe ſome of his deſired ends and practices. And he ſtands convict upon a full triall at the Aſſizes in Suffolke for the killing of a man, and was then conceived very foule againſt him, and was ſo proved by witneſſes in this deponents hearing.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>Iur. 4. die Auguſti 1641.</date>
                     <signed>Iohn Page.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
